Welcome students to the
supplemental video review of
the Check Your Knowledge
questions that are at the
end of each subclass of
diuretics. We will go through
all those explanations and
this will serve as a summary
to the diuretics lecture.
Dr. Goldstein speaking.
I'm here for you if you would
like to chat about
pharmacology.
and these are learning
objectives again just to remind
you what the goal of
diuretic therapy is which is
to restore and maintain
uvolemia by altering the
kidneys regulation of sodium
and water and you'll see
there are other therapeutic
uses for various diuretics
beginning with the principles.
Have a look at these
questions. You may want
to pause the video so
you can think about what
the answers are before
I give them to you.
So here they are.
What is the purpose of
diuretic use? What are
the effects of diuretic
use? And what are the
compensatory physiologic
effects that occur as a
result of diuretic use?
So, what is the purpose?
To decrease extracellular
fluid volume by
increasing sodium and
water excretion by the
kidneys with the goal of
restoring and maintaining
uvolemia and effective
circulating volume.
Sodium excretion is
called natriuresis.
Water excretion is
called diuresis.
What are the effects
of diuretic use?
Edema reduction.
The effects are
natriuresis and diuresis to
promote the movement of
fluid from the interstitial
space into the intravascular
compartment where
it can be excreted by
the kidneys and therefore
promote renal excretion
of this fluid, thereby
restoring normal effective
circulating volume.
For blood pressure,
this is for the
thiazide diuretics.
Diuretics reduce effective
circulating volume
by increasing renal sodium
and water excretion,
which lowers venous
return and cardiac output.
This is the initial effect.
Over time peripheral
vascular resistance decreases
and it is this feature that
provides the sustained
reduction in blood pressure.
Diuretics affect
electrolyte balance, sodium,
potassium, calcium,
magnesium, bicarbonate,
depending on the
particular diuretic.
And the magnitude
depends also on the dose.
The compensatory
physiologic effects,
volume depletion, we're
getting rid of a great
deal of sodium and water,
depending on the drug,
and that will cause the
volume depletion. And
the volume depletion
will activate the renin
angiotensin-aldosterone
system, and that will result
in aldosterone-enhanced
sodium and water
reabsorption, which counteracts
the diuretic effect.
Volume contraction
reduces plasma volume, and
this may stimulate secretion
of vasopressin, which
increases free water
reabsorption in the
collecting ducts, and
therefore water is reclaimed.
Where in the nephron do
the potassium wasting
and potassium sparing
effects of diuretics occur?
What is the key
determinant of potassium
secretion in the
distal nephron?
And then we have a
question for you.
We have a little tiny
case vignette. So
where does this
potassium effect occur?
Strongly regulated
by aldosterone in the
principal cells of
the late distal tubule
and collecting duct.
These are called the
aldosterone-sensitive
sites in the nephron.
What is the key
determinant of potassium
secretion in the
distal nephron?
Do you remember?
Here, increasing sodium
reabsorption by the
epithelial sodium channel
creates a lumen negative
transepithelial potential
that favors potassium
secretion out of the
cell through R-O-M-K
into the lumen, and then
potassium is excreted.
A 68-year-old man with
chronic heart failure
is treated with furosemide
for worsening leg
edema. After starting
ibuprofen for back pain,
his urine output
decreases and his weight
increases. What mechanism
best explains why ibuprofen
reduced the effectiveness
of his diuretic?
Well, you know what NSAIDs do.
They block the biosynthesis
of prostaglandin, and
this happens by inhibiting
cyclooxygenase 1 and 2.
PGE2 and PGI2 prostacyclin
are the major prostaglandins
expressed in the kidney.
by decreasing prostaglandin
synthesis that will
remove the prostaglandin
effect on afferent
arteriolar vasodilation which
will lead to afferent
vasoconstriction by the constrictive
agents that affected
norepinephrine angiotensin
2 and that in turn will
decrease renal blood flow
and decrease glomerular
filtration rate and by
decreasing GFR and that will
decrease diuretic delivery
for those that pass through
the glomerulus, leading
to a blunted diuretic
effect, but that's not all.
NSAIDs inhibit the organic
anion transporters,
reducing delivery
of the drug into
the proximal tubular
fluid, which is the
major way that diuretics
reach the tubule.
And NSAIDs cause
sodium and water
retention, reducing
diuretic efficacy.
Moving to the carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors,
carbonic anhydrase inhibitors
significantly increase
the excretion of what
electrolytes, so increase
urinary concentrations
of which electrolytes,
what is the effect of
carbonic anhydrase inhibitors
on the pH of the
blood, how is the CAI's
effect on blood pH used
to therapeutic advantage?
So, beginning with the
excretion of electrolytes,
carbonic anhydrase
inhibitors increase
urinary concentrations
of bicarbonate,
sodium, potassium, and calcium.
And this happens because
the function of carbonic
anhydrase is to reversibly
catalyze the forward and
reverse reaction of CO2
and water to carbonic acid,
both the membrane
bound on the luminal
side and within the
epithelial cell.
So carbonic anhydrase
is essential for the
reabsorption of 80 to 90
% of filtered bicarbonate
with the generation of
hydrogen ion, which drives
sodium reabsorption. So
this all gets blocked.
So bicarbonate is excreted,
sodium is excreted,
potassium is wasted,
so it's potassium
wasting effect,
and calcium is not
able to pass through
between the epithelial
cells, So it's
paracellular transport,
so that gets blocked,
and calcium levels
increase in the urine.
What is the effect on blood pH?
Well,
carbonic anhydrase inhibitors
do cause hyperchloremic
metabolic acidosis, which
is mild, but it's still
acidosis. increased excretion
of bicarbonate in the
urine reduces serum bicarbonate
which is a key buffer in
maintaining pH of the blood
leading to mild metabolic
acidosis and reabsorption
of filtered chloride
increases to maintain
electron electroneutrality so
bicarbonate is not reabsorbed
so chloride is reabsorbed,
which leads to a relative
increase in serum chloride.
Thus, carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors
cause hyperchloremic
metabolic acidosis.
Now I have an extra
question here.
So it causes a mild metabolic
acidosis. What is
the pH of the urine?
Well, it's alkaline.
Correct? It's putting
all that bicarbonate
in there. Now
think for a minute.
Calcium in alkaline urine,
what is that going to cause?
Calcium phosphate
precipitation.
So crystals, calcium phosphate
crystals, and what
will that cause?
Kidney stones.
So carbonic anhydrase
inhibitor use can
increase the risk of
kidney stones, particularly
in people who are
at risk for them.
And the last question
on this slide, How is
the carbonic anhydrase
inhibitor's effect
on blood pH used to
therapeutic advantage?
And that is for the
prevention and treatment
of acute mountain
sickness, which is
also known as acute
altitude sickness.
Mild metabolic acidosis
stimulates ventilation,
increasing CO2
exhalation, which sustains
hyperventilation and
enhances oxygenation.
so the high-altitude
symptoms diminish.
Why do carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors
cause only mild
diuresis? Why is the
diuretic effect of
CAIs self-limited?
Why is the action of
CAIs not self-limited in
the treatment of glaucoma
and mountain sickness?
In terms of only mild
diuresis, remembering that
it is blocking a large
fraction of sodium that
would normally be
reabsorbed in the proximal
tubule. Well, that sodium
gets reabsorbed itself
in the more distal
portions of the nephron as
it goes through the
sick ascending limb, the
distal convoluted tubule
and the principal cells.
The nephron, so that's
all here. So by the time
the sodium load reaches
the collecting tubules
for excretion, it's
only a quite a small
percentage and therefore
mild natriuresis and diuresis
occurs. So why is the
effect self-limited?
after 2, 3, 4 days,
something like that.
Inhibition of carbonic
anhydrase leads to
bicarbonate loss in
urine, metabolic acidosis.
Over time, plasma
bicarbonate decreases,
filtered bicarbonate
load falls, and
with its sodium
excretion is reduced.
the extracellular fluid
volume contraction plus
metabolic acidosis
stimulates aldosterone
secretion. Thinking
aldosterone, think about
reabsorption in the principal
cells via the epithelial
sodium channel. So these
are upregulated and
that will increase
sodium reabsorption even
further, limiting natriuretic
and diuretic effect.
Thus, diuretic
efficacy is reduced.
Well, why isn't it self-limited
in these other conditions?
Acute mountain sickness
treatment is due to the
induction of metabolic
acidosis, and metabolic
acidosis is not self
-limited. Because as long as
the carbonic anhydrase
inhibitor is present, the
bicarbonate reabsorption
will be blocked. and
buffering capacity of the
blood is also depleted.
And in glaucoma, the
reason that carbonic
anhydrase inhibitor
is not self-limited,
the effect is not self
-limited, is because the goal
for this is to reduce the
formation of bicarbonate. and
it is bicarbonate formation
that is important for
aqueous humor production and
that gets blocked. So that
will reduce aqueous humor
production. A lower amount
of aqueous humor will reduce
the pressure in the eye.
A little case
vignette. A 28-year-old
first-time mountain climber
starts acetazolamide
for prevention
of acute mountain
sickness before ascending
to high altitude.
Two days later, he
reports a tingling pins
and needles sensation
in his fingers and
around his lips, but
otherwise feels well.
What is the side effect likely
caused by the medication?
And what is the mechanistic
rationale for the medication
for this purpose, meaning
acute mountain sickness?
Well, it's paresthesia.
The pins and needles
sensation is paresthesia.
The mechanism,
the clinical rationale,
is because with rapid
ascent to high elevation,
the body doesn't have
time to adjust to the
lower oxygen pressure.
So a person can get headache
and nausea, vomiting,
fatigue, dizziness,
and sleep disturbance.
The body responds to
hypoxia, sensed by
peripheral chemoreceptors,
with hyperventilation.
CO2 exhalation leads to
hypocapnia, which leads
to respiratory
alkalosis, which prevents
peripheral chemoreceptors
and inhibits the respiratory
center, limiting further
hyperventilation.
So by inducing a mild
metabolic acidosis, that
will stimulate these
peripheral chemoreceptors and
the respiratory center,
which will increase the
minute ventilation, and
that will lead to sustained
hyperventilation with
approved oxygenation and
therefore the high
-altitude symptoms diminish.
Moving now to loop
diuretics and the
thick ascending limb
NKCC2 inhibition.
How does blocking the
NKCC2 lead to high efficacy
diuresis what are the
mechanisms of the loop diuretics
effect on urinary electrolytes
loop diuretics can cause
metabolic alkalosis what
is the mechanism so let's
get to it so high efficacy
diuresis because approximately
25% of sodium reabsorption
occurs in the thick
ascending limb and blocking
this transporter, NKCC2,
results in profound and rapid
matrioresis and
diuresis. High efficacy.
What are the
mechanisms of the loop
diuretics effect on
urinary electrolytes?
NKCC2 prevents reabsorption
of sodium chloride and
potassium, obviously
from the name, and it
eliminates the positive lumen
potential, preventing the
paracellular transport
of calcium and magnesium.
Therefore,
sodium, chloride,
potassium, calcium,
and magnesium are
excreted in the urine.
And metabolic alkalosis, how
do loop diuretics cause it?
Through potassium loss,
so it's a hypokalemic
metabolic alkalosis,
and increased hydrogen
secretion and the
potassium movement through
the ROMK and hydrogen
secretion are regulated
by aldosterone along
with volume contraction,
RAS activation that
promotes proximal
tubule bicarbonate
reabsorption.
Hypocloremia impairs bicarbonate
excretion and increased
hydrogen and secretion
generates and retains
bicarbonate maintaining loop
diuretic induced alkalosis.
What are the
contributors to edema
refractory to loop
diuretic therapy?
Which patients
are susceptible to
loop diuretic refractory edema?
What is the mechanism
by which loop diuretics
impair the kidney's
ability to produce
dilute urine during
high intake of water,
and concentrated urine
during hydropenia.
So let's first talk
about refractory edema.
The contributors are
several, so I'm thinking from
the beginning as the patient
swallows the medication.
Gut edema, which occurs
in heart failure patients
because there's edema
there and and makes it
a further distance for
the medication to pass
through the gut and get
to the portal circulation.
So that will reduce
drug absorption.
Compensatory
sodium reabsorption
that occurs after
the drug wears off.
Distal nephron hypertrophy
and upregulation of sodium
transporters in distal
tubule enhances sodium
reabsorption. and this is
really the primary mechanism
right here, this distal
nephron increase in sodium
reabsorption.
Volume contraction can
lead to reduced renal
perfusion, which decreases
drug concentration at the
site of action because
less drug is delivered.
Persistent activation of
sympathetic nervous system
and renal angiotensin and
aldosterone system leads to
aldosterone mediated sodium
and water reabsorption and
decreased blood volume,
increased plasma osmolality,
stimulates vasopressin
-induced water
reabsorption in the
collecting tubules,
especially in
patients with heart
failure, cirrhosis,
or nephrotic syndrome.
Patients with heart
failure, chronic kidney
disease, liver cirrhosis
with ascites, nephrotic
syndrome, secondary
hyperaldosteronism are frequent
reasons for refractoriness
to loop diuretics.
And dilute urine versus
concentrated urine.
Well, normally the
thick ascending limb
absorbs solutes without
water because the
TAL is impermeable
to water. So it just
reabsorbs through the
NKCC, those solutes.
And that would normally, so by
reabsorption of the
solutes, that dilutes
the tubular fluid.
So that's normal.
Blocking the NKCC2 disables
this process. So now
the solutes are not
reabsorbed, they stay in the
fluid, so the fluid is
not dilute any longer, and
therefore the body cannot
excrete a dilute urine,
even when a person takes
in a high amount of water.
We're just increasing
those solutes in the urine.
Loop diuretics
abolish the medullary
osmotic gradient, so
water reabsorption
from the collecting
tubule is limited.
And therefore, urine can't
be concentrated when water
intake is low, even when
vasopressin is present.
Question, case vignette.
A 75-year-old male
with hypertension
and heart failure is
taking lisinopril,
which is an angiotensin
-converting enzyme
inhibitor, and furosemide.
After self-treating
chronic knee pain with
naproxen, the patient
develops dizziness
and a sharp rise in
serum creatinine.
Explain the mechanism
of the drug-drug
interaction leading to
the adverse drug event.
well it's a triple hit
blocking prostaglandin
biosynthesis plus blocking
angiotensin 2 effects plus
decreasing effective
circulating volume leads to
collapse of glomerular
filtration pressure and gfr and
that increases the risk
of acute kidney injury so
how is this happening
NSAIDs block prostaglandin
-mediated afferent dilation,
leading to afferent
constriction, which decreases
glomerular filtration
pressure, which decreases
glomerular filtration rate,
risking acute kidney injury.
The RAS inhibitors,
particularly the ones that
are first-line, ACE
inhibitors and angiotensin
receptor blockers,
block the angiotensin
II-mediated efferent
constriction. So the efferent
arteriole is dilated.
And that dilation,
along with the constriction
by the NSAID, will
really decrease glomerular
filtration pressure in
GFR, increasing the risk
of acute kidney injury.
And diuretics cause
effective circulating
volume depletion,
leading to reduced, well,
effective circulating volume.
And that, in turn, will lead
to decreased renal blood flow,
decreased glomerular
filtration pressure in GFR,
and further increasing the
risk of acute kidney injury.
Effective circulating
volume depletion
activates RAS, but
RAS inhibitors,
renin-angiotensin
system inhibitors,
ACE inhibitors and ARBs,
block angiotensin II effects.
by different mechanisms should
be E effective
circulating volume ECB ECB
I hate acronyms as
you know and that
concludes the review
questions for part one
PowerPoint has the
answers to the questions